Finding Aid for the John Thompson Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John Thompson Papers
1941-1945
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0450
.42 linear feet
Biography/History
John Thompson, a native of Nashville, was a graduate of the former Wallace School. He attended Vanderbilt University and received a B.A. in 1930 and M.A. in 1932. He then attended Harvard Law School. In 1933 he joined the staff of the Tennessean, where he became an editorial writer and a day city editor. He also was a night manager of the Associated Press Nashville Bureau. In 1942, he enlisted in the United States Navy for service in World War II. In 1944 he was promoted to Lieutenant, and was discharged with the rank of Lieutenant Commander. In 1945, he wrote a weekly newsletter for the naval post squadron and wings. He was stationed in Alaska, and later assigned to a naval cruiser in the Pacific.
John Thompson was active in many cultural and theatrical activities, including a two-term president of the Nashville Community Playhouse. He died in 1977.
Scope and Contents
This .21 linear feet collection contains 63 letters, two postcards, and one V-Mail Christmas Card from John Thompson to several family members while serving in the United States Navy during World War II. The letters are arranged in file folders chronologically by year, then month.
- Correspondence – Outgoing – to Mrs. Samuel H. Orr (Mimi)
  - typed letter w/envelope, March 21, 1941
  - postcard, January 20, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, February 4, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, February 6, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, February 17, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, February 21, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, March 3, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, March 8, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, March 14, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, April 1, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, April 5, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, April 8, 1942
  - handwritten letter, April 21, 1942
  - handwritten letter, April 29, 1942
  - handwritten letter, April 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, May 12, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, May 14, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, May 26, 1942
  - handwritten letter, June 15, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, June 17, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, July 2, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, July 4, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, July 10, 1943
  - typed letter, July 25, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, August 19, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, August 24, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, August 31, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, September 5, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, September 7, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, September 26, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, October 24, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, November 11, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, November 28, 1942
  - typed letter w/envelope, December 18, 1942
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, January 27, 1943
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, February 12, 1943
  - typed letter w/envelope, April 14, 1943
  - typed letter w/envelope, May 29, 1943
  - typed letter w/envelope, June 22, 1943
  - typed letter, August 16, 1943
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, September 19, 1943
  - typed letter w/envelope, October 4, 1943
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, November 1, 1943
  - V-Mail Christmas card, December 4, 1943
  - handwritten letter, January 9, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, January 19, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, February 23, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, April 5, 1944
  - handwritten postcard, April 6, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, April 16, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, May 8, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, May 27, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, June 17, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, July 1, 1944
  - typed letter w/envelope, August 6, 1944
  - typed letter w/envelope, August 16, 1944
  - typed letter w/envelope, August 29, 1944
  - handwritten letter, September 14, 1944
  - handwritten letter, September 28, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, October 29, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, December 6, 1944
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, March 20, 1945
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, July 26, 1945
  - Correspondence – Outgoing – to Uncle Billy
  - handwritten letter, April 28, 1942
  - handwritten letter, May 21, 1942
  - Correspondence – Incoming – from Cora H. West
  - handwritten letter w/envelope, December 14, 1943